A Guide to the David H. Stevens Papers FA051
Rockefeller Archive Center
David H. Stevens papers
1929-1976 (bulk 1929-1950)
bulk
Rockefeller Archive Center
Stevens, David Harrison
FA051
2 Cubic Feet 4 letter document cases 1 1/2 letter document case
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The David H. Stevens Papers are divided into two series:
Series 1 - Personal Papers
Series 2 - Rockefeller Foundation Records
Biographical/Historical note
Educator and author, David Harrison Stevens was born on December 20, 1884, in Berlin, Wisconsin. He received his undergraduate (1906) and master's (1910) degrees from Lawrence College, a second master's degree from Harvard University (1912), and the Ph.D. in English from the University of Chicago (1914). During his undergraduate years, he met Ruth Frances Davis, whom he married on March 26, 1915. Their family included three children.
After a brief tenure as Instructor of English at Northwestern University (1908-1912), Dr. Stevens received a similar post at the University of Chicago, where he rose to Professor of English and later Associate Dean of Faculties. During this period, interrupted briefly by military service in World War I, he published scholarly studies on Milton and Restoration drama.
On October 19, 1929, Dr. Stevens was named Director of Education for the General Education Board. The following year, he became Vice President of that organization, a position he held until May 20, 1938.
At the beginning of 1932, Dr. Stevens was appointed the first full-time Director of the Humanities Division of The Rockefeller Foundation. Under his leadership, Foundation appropriations for the humanities developed from a series of random grants into full-scale programs of library support, creative work in drama, film, and radio, and intensive training in modern languages and foreign culture. Dr. Stevens retired from the Foundation on December 31, 1949.
During his retirement years, Dr. Stevens continued his active interest in education and authorship, producing two books: "The Changing Humanities" (1953, later title "A Time for Humanities," 1969) and "Ten Talents in the American Theatre" (1957). In 1967, he and his wife endowed the Stevens Lectureship in the Humanities at Lawrence University. Dr. Stevens died in La Jolla, California, on January 29, 1980.
Scope and Contents note
The David H. Stevens papers contain little material of a personal nature. Consisting of reports, correspondence, pamphlets, articles, speeches, and a book manuscript, the papers focus narrowly upon Stevens's term as Director of the Humanities Division of The Rockefeller Foundation (1932-1949) and upon some of his retirement activities. Such correspondence as exists in this collection is mainly concerned with Stevens's contacts among Foundation personnel and grantees or the disposition of his papers with the Foundation archives. Approximately eighty percent of the material in this collection consists of reports and other records related to the operations of the Humanities Division. None of the material relates to Stevens's service with the General Education Board.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 2A 34
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
David H. Stevens donated his papers to The Rockefeller Foundation between 1969 and 1975.
Humanities; Stevens, David Harrison; Rockefeller Foundation
- Personal Papers, 1933-1976; 1; 0.5 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence (dating from Stevens's retirement years), articles and speeches, and the manuscript of a book entitled "Something about Education."
  - Correspondence, 1959-1962, 1967-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Articles and Speeches, 1933-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Book Manuscript - "Something about Education", circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book Manuscript - "Something about Education", circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Rockefeller Foundation Records, 1929-1975; 2; 1.5 Cubic Feet
  This series contains records of appropriations for the Humanities Division compiled from the Minutes of the Foundation from 1929 until 1949, Humanities Program reviews and fellowship surveys undertaken between 1934 and 1949, and occasional reports. Also contained in this series are reports generated from other divisions of the Foundation or treating the Humanities Division as part of the Foundation's general program. A small number of pamphlets collected by Stevens dealing with Foundation grantees concludes this series. Most of the material in this series is duplicated in the archives of The Rockefeller Foundation.
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1929-1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1936-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Humanities Appropriations, 1945-1949 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Humanities Program Reviews, 1934-1947 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Humanities Program Reviews, 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Humanities Division - Survey of Fellowships, 1933-1948 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Humanities Division - Reports, 1943-1949, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Report of Committee on Appraisal and Plan, 1934; Report of Special Committee on Policy and Program, 1946-1947.
  - Rockefeller Foundation - General Reports, 1935, 1940,1944 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Pamphlets Relating to Grantees, 1946-1950 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Rockefeller Foundation - Pamphlets Relating to Grantees, 1955, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 19)